A Guide to the Donald R. Griffin papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA164
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Correspondence, 1
  - Suthers, Roderick A. (Box 12, Folder 125)
    Alpha Helix; bats; Beebe Tropical Station; birds; Julia Chase; Chillagoe; equipment; Indiana University School of Medicine; Konstantinov; Andrew Meyerreicks; National Institutes of Health; National Science Foundation; New York Zoological Society; Alvin Novick; David Pye; Queensland; Scripps Institution of Oceanography; Simla; Trinidad; U.S. Public Health Service; Richard Wylie
  - Ta-Ty (Box 13, Folder 126)
    Taber, Wendell - Frances Burnett; Minnesota Mining;. Tamkin, Arthur S. - Veterans' Administration Hospital; bird conditioning experiments; Skinner; Yeagley; pigeon orientation. Tatum, Edward L. - Rockefeller University; Philosophical Society. Tavolga, W. N. - Mote Marine Laboratory; fish acoustic orientation. Taylor, Bonnie - Phoenix Zoo; Edinburgh Zoo; Scotland; dog and horse communication; blind children; Rockefeller University. Taylor, C. Richard - Harvard University Museum of Comparative Zoology; Jose Torre-Bueno. Taylor, Robert - citations. Teakle, Harold P. - E. J. Maxwell Lumber; bat sight. Telesonic Systems - bats and sound waves; Carlsbad Caverns; National Park Service. Terres, John K. - National Audubon Society; bats and tall buildings, radio/TV wave effects. Test, Frederick H. - University of Michigan; Venezuelan bats. Teuber, Hans-Lukas - Massachusetts Institute of Technology; bird navigation. Thaeler, Charles - Earlham College; Cornell University. Theodorides, J. - Museum National (No Suggestions) Naturelle; Paris; bats; Harvard University; cave photos. Thomas, Don - University of Washington; old forests and bats; kite-balloon; kytoon;. Thomas, Steven P. - bat supplies; bird tracking; Duke University; Duquesne University; Robert Mackie; National Science Foundation; Alvin Novick; James Simmons; Jose Torre-Bueno; Trinidad; wind tunnel. Thomas, Stiles - Rich Penney; Society for the Preservation of Birds of Prey; hawk migration; Ron Larkin. Thomas, Thurlo B. - Phillips Exeter Academy; William Harvey. Thompson, E. Fontelle - University of South Carolina. Thompson, M. N. - United Kingdom Meteorological Office; bird orientation. Thompson, W. F. - University of Washington Fisheries Research Institute; salmon homing;. Thompson, William R. - Cone Island, Maine; gulls. Thomson, Sir Landsborough - London; reprint. Thorpe, William H. - University of Cambridge; Harvard University; Pennycuick; Hatch; radio transmitters for birds; Poland; Ibis; Trinidad; Cornell University. Thurston, E. G. - Batelle Memorial Institute; transducer equipment. Timm, C. - Universitat Mainz; Germany; bat and moth echolocation; World War II. Tinbergen, Nikolaas - Ruksuniversiteit te Leiden; bird homing;. Tomasi, Thomas - University of Rhode Island; shrew echolocation; sound equipment. Topal, G. - Hungarian Natural History Museum; bat migration; Calvin Stillman; Harvard Ornithological Club. Torre-Bueno, Jose - Duke University; Woods Hole; bird flow patterns. Torrey, Henry - Rutgers University; bird navigation; physics. Tosteson, Thomas - University of Puerto Rico. Tracerlab - J. Kohl; radioactive isotopes in bird migration. Tracy, C. Richard - University of Wisconsin; Hammel; heat loss from mammals. Treat, Asher - bat ultrasonic cries; bat visual acuity; moths; City College, New York; Sir Cyril A. Clarke. Trembley, F. T. - Lehigh University; owls. Trempe, Duke - birds; Michigan. Tuck, Leslie - Canadian Wildlife service; bird navigation. Tucker, Richard - University of Queensland; Australia; veterinary science; bat orientation. Tucker, Vance A. - Duke University; bird gliding versus flapping; radar; Torre-Bueno; Millbrook, NY; NASA; wind tunnels; American Philosophical Society;. Tufts, Robie W. - bird migration; Bay of Fundy; Canada. Turner, Dennis C. - Johns Hopkins University; bat ecology. Turner, Ruth - Clapp Laboratories. Tuttle, Merlin D. - Milwaukee Public Museum; bat migration. Twente, John W., Jr. - University of Michigan; bat orientation. Twersky, Victor - New York University; guidance device for blind; audible click equipment. Twitty, Victor C. - Stanford University; homing of newts. Tyack, Peter - dolphins; France; Woods Hole.
  - Trapido, Harold (Box 13, Folder 127)
    see also Projects-Panama; see also Projects-Bat Banding; Cornell University; bat banding; bat longevity; Canal Zone Corrosion Laboratory; Empire Devices; Gorgas Memorial Institute of Tropical and Preventive Medicine; Ed Gould; India; mines; Panama; U.S. Naval Station; Bill Wimsatt; Rockefeller Foundation
  - Trotter, Eleonora D'Arms (Box 13, Folder 128)
    Rockefeller University; balloon capture of bird sounds; bird mobbing behavior; University of New Mexico; University of Washington; Queensland; Bohemia Lumber Co.; New York Zoological Society; Garrett Eddy; Roy Talmage
  - U-V (Box 13, Folder 129)
    Udvardy, Miklos D. F. - University of British Columbia; radioactive tagging; recording equipment. Ulmer, Frederic A., Jr. - Zoological Society of Philadelphia; echolocation. Utter, Katharyn - University of Washington; gibbons. Van Cleve, R. - University of Washington; salmon; U.S. Army Corps of Engineers; Alaska; Lissmann; Vladimir Walters; Breder; Raney; Easton. Van der Kloot, William - Lalor Foundation; Cornell University. Van Gelder, Richard G. - University of Illinois; Museum of Natural History, Kansas; bat collection; Alvin Novick; Sben Dijkgraaf; see also Publishers. Van Riper, Walker - Colorado Museum of Natural History; birds. Van Tilla, Marvin - bird navigation. van Tyne, Josselyn - University of Michigan; birds. Varma, D. P. - Dalhousie University; Canada; bats;. Vencl, Frederic V. - birds. Venn, Mary Adrian - bees. Verduin, Mrs. E. - bats in France. Villa-Ramirez, Bernardo - Mexican Wildlife Service; Yucatan visit; radar; kite balloons; sound recording. Vinalhaven Port District - ferries; Maine. Vleugel, D. A. - Holland; The Hague; birds. Voelker, John D. - bat radar and spinning fishing rods. Vogel, Howard H., Jr. - Vanderbilt University; radio tracking birds; University of Tennessee; Point Barrow, Alaska; Charles Walcott; Bermuda. von Gierke, Henning E. - Wright-Patterson Air Force Base, Ohio; Aero Medical Laboratory; furred animals. von Holst, Erich - Max Planck Institut. von Saint Paul, Ursula - Duke University; Rawson; Mayr. Voute, Aldo M. - Rijksuniversiteit; Holland; Holgate instruments.
  - Unidentified (Box 13, Folder 130)
    Alden; Floyd; Fred; Garth; Harriett; Ian; Jane; Johann; Louise; Mattiot; Rosamund; Ruth; Stacey (Hustace); Warren; Barnard College; Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique; Phillips Academy; Kenyon College; Harvard University; Milton Academy; UCLA; University of California-San Diego; University of London; Yale University
  - U.S. Agencies (Box 13, Folder 131)
    Aberdeen Proving Ground; Agricultural Research Service; Air Force Office of Scientific Research; Alaska; Army Chemical Center; Army Ordnance Department; Bureau of Biological Survey; Carlsbad Caverns; Department of Health, Education, and Welfare; Federal Security Agency; Fish and Wildlife Service; Harvard University Fatigue Lab; Irwin Goldstein; MIT; Midway Atoll; Military Air Transport Service; National Institute of Health; National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration; National Park Service; Navy Bureau of Aeronautics; Public Health Service; South Pacific Fisheries Investigations; Southwest Rabies consultation; Billings; Denny Constantine; David B. Dill; H. F. Fraser; H. Frings; I. A. Getting; Freeman F. Hall; Arthur Hasler; Blanche Johnson; Thomas H. Johnson; Donald Kennedy; Herman Kleerekoper; William Krummes; John Marr; W. L. McAtee; James Moulton; Sidney Newman; Streicher; Joseph F. Winkler; aircraft damage by birds; bird orientation; mammalogy
  - United States Office of Naval Research (Box 13, Folder 132)
    American Museum of Natural History; bird and bee homing; Canal Zone; Cornell University; Mt. Hope Mine; Naval Medical Center; Panama; Rockefeller University; Shahmoon Industries; Zoologisches Institut; Lester Aronson; H. M. Auerbach; S. Galler; Arthur Hasler; H. T. Meryman; Novick; Don Schneirla; C. W. Shilling; Trapido; Richard Tousey; Von Frisch
  - Von Frisch, Karl (Box 13, Folder 133)
    American Philosophical Society; Cornell University; Nobel Prize; Rockefeller Foundation; U. S. Department of Agriculture; Yale University Press; Zoologisches Institut der Universitat, Germany; bees; Niels Bohr; Viktor Hamburger; Hasler; August Krogh; library resupply; Anne Roe; U.S. lecture tour; Roberta Yerkes; see also U.S. Office of Naval Research
  - Wa-Wh (Box 14, Folder 134)
    Wacker, Peter - Elizabeth Marsh; Julia Chase; Rutgers University; Society of Women Geographers. Wagner, Charles N. - bat sound transmission. Walker, Gene B. - University of Oklahoma; atmospheric acoustics; NOAA; NASA. Walker, Paul A. - Randolph-Macon Woman's College. Walker, Theodore J. - McMaster University; Altec Corp.; fish noises; Scripps Institution for Oceanography; University of California; John Hilliard; Kleerekoper; William Cheville; Woods Hole. Wallace, John D. - Thomas Jefferson University Hospital; microphones. Wallingford, Daniel Kirkwood - industrial design; Cornell University; maps. Wallraff, Hans G. - Max Planck Institut; conditioned heart rate method. Walsh, Raymond R. - American Physiological Society; University of Colorado; Brookhaven National Laboratory; Cornell University; Northwestern University; sensory physiology. Walter, H. William - luminous bands. Walter, Waldemar M. - bird homing; radio transmitting stations; U. S. Army. Warner, Walter R. - Canton Center Congregational Church; bats in church. Waser, Peter - Purdue University; primate vocalization. Washburn, Sherwood L. - University of Chicago. Waterman, Talbot H. - Yale University; Cornell University. Watkins, Elwyn Mrs. - bats in house. Weatherly, W. Paul - Rockefeller University; Sri Lanka; U.S. Agency for International Development; flying fox; Millbrook, NY; Academy of Natural Science, Philadelphia. Webb, George - Woods Hole. Webb, Glenn R. - University of Kansas; radio waves. Weisz, Paul B. - Brown University; bat and fan. Welch, William A. - hawk migration; motor glider; Smirnoff Vodka; Connecticut Audubon Council. Welker, W. I. - University of Wisconsin; bat auditory system. Weller, Thomas H. - Boston Children's Hospital; bat research; rabies. Welsh, John H. - University of Cambridge; Harvard University; bat research; see also Harvard Biological Laboratory. Welter, Wilfred A. - Morehead State Teachers College; bat banding. Wendt, G. R. - University of Rochester; motion sickness. Wenzel, Bernice M. - UCLA; Papi; pigeon homing. Westby, G. W. Max - Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique, France; electric fish behavior. Westenberg, J. - Netherlands Zoologisch Station, Holland; fish acoustics. Wever, E. G. - Princeton University; sound instruments; auditory sensitivity of insects. Wheeler, Bernice - Yale University; bat film. Whitacre, David - University of California, Davis; bat falcon.
  - Wi-Wy (Box 14, Folder 135)
    Wiesel, Torsten N. - Harvard Medical School; Society for Neuroscience; Federal funding; National Institutes of Health; Martha Constantine-Paton. Wiley, Haven - University of North Carolina; sound transmission; Axel Michelson;. Willams, C. B. - Rothamsted Experimental Station, England; bird navigation. Williams, Carroll M. - Harvard University; insect endocrinology. Williams, Clarence J. - bat book; Air Force counter-measure. Williams, Timothy and Janet - see also Projects-Beebe Tropical Station and Woods Hole; State University of New York, Buffalo. Wilson, David Sloan - Michigan State University; evolutionary theory. Wilson, Don E. - University of New Mexico; bat homing; U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service; National Museum of Natural History; Costa Rica. Wilson, Thomas - birds and Allentown airport tower. Wilsson, Lars - beaver behavior; Sweden. Wing, Leonard - State College of Washington. Wingate, David B. - Bermuda Department of Agriculture and Fisheries; NASA radar project; bird migration; Jeremy Hatch. Winn, Howard E. - University of Maryland; echolocation. Wittenberg University - Powelson, Elizabeth E.. Wodzicki, Count K. A. - Consulate General, Poland; bird homing; R. J. Wojtusiak; New Zealand Department of Scientific and Industrial Research. Wojtusiak, R. J. - University of Cracow; bird navigation; K. A. Wodzicki. Wolf, Ernst - Wellesley College; von Frisch. Wolfson, Albert - Northwestern University; ornithology book. Wood, Meridth, Jr. - kites; Millbrook, NY. Wood, Sherwin F. - Los Angeles City College; bat diseases. Woodbury, Angus M. - University of Utah; pelican nesting sites; migration theory. Woodbury, David T. - Psycho-acoustic laboratory; Merck and Co.. Woodcock, Alfred - University of Hawaii; NASA radar; Woods Hole; Alpha Helix; bird navigation; Duncan Blanchard; Atmospheric Sciences Research Center; Office of Naval Research; State University of New York, Albany; Alfred Redfield. Wood-Gush, David G. M. - Poultry research Center; Scotland. Woolf, Nigel - Cornell University; bird echolocation; Alpha Helix; tape recordings. World Wide Broadcasting Foundation - brochure. Worth, C. Brooke - Rockefeller Foundation; bird migration and stars; Cape May, NJ property. Wright, Albert Hazen and Anna - Penikese Island. Wright, Nellie M. - bats in various states. WVHC Radio Station - Hofstra University; animal to man communication program. Wylie, Richard M. - Walter Reed Army Medical Center; sub-auditory sound. Wyman, Louise - bats in house.
  - Walcott, Charles (Box 14, Folder 136)
    Cornell University; pigeon homing; animal thinking; Martin Michener; State University of New York, Stoney Brook; National Geographic Society; bat films; New York Zoological Society
  - Wimsatt, William (Box 14, Folder 137)
    Cornell University; Harold Trapido; Carl Engler; P.E. Crowe; tropical bats; Brookhaven National Laboratory; Mexico; Life Magazine; Beebe Tropical Station, Trinidad; John H. Hughes; U.S. Public Health Service; see also Publishers-Academic Press, Inc.
  - X-Z (Box 14, Folder 138)
    Yacobi, V. E. - USSR Academy of Science; Torre-Bueno; bird navigation and radar. Yarmouth Town, Massachusetts - bounties for seals. Yarwood, T. M. - England; ultrasonic bat sounds. Yeagley, Henry L. - homing pigeon orientation; Pennsylvania State College; National Science Foundation; Army Signal Corps; Office of Naval Research. Yerkes Regional Primate Research Center - Duane M. Rumbaugh; language formation studies. Yerkes, Robert M. - Yale University; von Frisch;. Yonge, C. M. - University of Glasgow; Herbert Hillman; University of California. Zander, H. A. - Tufts College Dental School; bat experiments with tissue drug reaction. Zhukov, Dr. - Konstantinov; USSR; Leningrad University;. Zuloaga, Guillermo - Venezuela; acoustic orientation of guacharos; photographs.
  - Yodlowski, Marilyn (Box 14, Folder 139)
    Harvard Medical School; pigeon sound sensitivity; Woods Hole; Johns Hopkins University; Fernando Nottebohm; T. J. Sejnowski; Rockefeller University; Carl Pfaffmann; Kreithen; Cornell University; Grass Polygraph
- Projects, 2
  Alphabetical by name of project.
  Series 2 contains correspondence regarding projects not part of routine work at Cornell, Harvard, or Rockefeller University that have a sufficient quantity of pertinent documents to warrant separation.
  Adams Bat Bomb -
  In 1942, while a research associate at Harvard, Griffin conducted preliminary research to determine the viability of using bats to carry small bombs. Although he concluded that the project was not feasible, the idea’s promoter, Lytle Adams, continued to pursue his proposal and the concept gained considerable public attention.
  Arctic Aeromedical Laboratory -
  During the winters of 1950-51, 1951-52, and 1952-53, Griffin and his assistants studied effects of wind on insulation of fur in animals, gastro-intestinal tract heat production, and other aspects relevant to man’s ability to survive in cold temperatures. Research was conducted under Air Force contract AF 33(038)-12764, at Ladd Air Force Base, Fairbanks, Alaska.
  Arctic Research Laboratory/Arctic Institute of North America -
  In the summer of 1947 and 1948, Griffin conducted homing experiments studying bird orientation and sensory physiology. Work was funded by the U.S. Office of Naval Research and based at Point Barrow, Alaska.
  Alpha Helix Expedition -
  In the summer of 1969, Griffin began a four-month trip to New Guinea on the vessel Alpha Helix (owned by Scripps Institution of Oceanography) where he studied bats and cave swiftlets. The expedition was operated by the University of California with funding from the National Science Foundation. Griffin was in the crew headed by George Bartholomew that included fellow scientists Jocelyn Crane (Griffin’s wife), Jared Diamond of UCLA, Alan Grinnell of UCLA, Susumu Hagiwara, Bodil Schmidt-Nielsen, and Hobart van Deusen.
  Austin Ornithological Research Station -
  Over the course of several years beginning in 1933 and extending into the mid-1950s, Griffin banded birds, primarily terns and herring gulls, on Penikese Island, Massachusetts observing obstacle avoidance and homing instincts. The studies were done in conjunction with Griffin’s university affiliations and Woods Hole Marine Biological Laboratory.
  Bat Banding -
  Griffin began banding bats while a high school student and continued for at least two decades, finding colonies in mines and caves throughout the Northeast and in Kentucky, Ohio, Pennsylvania, and Canada. Data about banded bats was still being returned as late as 1956 and informed new understanding of bat longevity, hibernation, and migration. Some of the banding activities were conducted in connection with Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution and correspondence about that work is included in the Bat Banding project folder.
  Beebe Tropical Research Station -
  Between July 1960 and August 1969, Griffin made several trips to the Beebe Tropical Research Station in Simla, Trinidad studying bat visual detection and echolocation and fish-catching bat abilities. The Station was operated jointly with the New York Zoological Society and some of the research was funded by the National Science Foundation. Griffin’s wife, Jocelyn Crane, conducted research into fiddler crab behavior there. Griffin and Crane shared responsibility for the facility’s scientific work.
  Bowdoin Scientific Station -
  Beginning in the 1930s and continuing into the 1950s, Griffin and colleagues took trips to the Bowdoin Scientific Station’s Kent Island facility in the Bay of Fundy, New Brunswick, Canada where they studied bird homing and navigation, especially in petrels and gannets.
  Chillagoe Expedition -
  In summer 1980, Griffin was one of several international scientists in the Chillagoe Expedition, a U. S. National Science Foundation sponsored trip to Queensland, Australia for the study of sensory physiology and perception in bats, bowerbirds, and cave swiftlets.
  Huyck Preserve -
  In 1939, Griffin received a summer fellowship at the Edmund Niles Huyck Preserve in Rensselaerville, New York, and later published journal articles based on his bat banding and research there.
  Panama -
  In the spring of 1953, Griffin and a Harvard student, Prentice Bloedel (“Pen”) spent two months researching and filming tropical fish-catching bats in Panama. Bloedel continued for a few more months. Griffin’s former student, Harold Trapido with the Gorgas Memorial Laboratory in Panama was a key contact for the project. Griffin periodically imported bats from there and some of his students visited to research. The U.S. Office of Naval Research sponsored some of Griffin’s work in the Canal Zone.
  Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution -
  Beginning as early as 1945 and extending into the 1970s, Griffin conducted independent research, usually during summers, at Woods Hole investigating a variety of topics including bat navigation, bird orientation, and radar tracking. The U.S. Office of Naval Research supported Griffin’s research on bat radar in the summer of 1953 and a few years earlier when he investigated fish hearing. Correspondence about bat banding and monitoring activities based from Woods Hole is included in the Bat Banding project folder. Although not connected to a specific project, correspondence related to Griffin’s service as an Associate in Physiology of the WHOI is included in this folder.
  - Adams Bat Bomb (Box 14, Folder 140)
    Lytle S. Adams; J. C. Von Bloeker; James B. Conant; Harvard University Psycho-Acoustical Laboratory; Los Angeles City College; True Magazine; Jim Chester; National Defense Research Committee
  - Alpha Helix, New Guinea (Box 14, Folder 141)
    American Museum of Natural History; George Bartholomew; bat and bird orientation; Theodore Bullock; Jared Diamond; Alan Grinnell; Susumu Hagiwara; Tom Harrisson; Ernst Mayr; H. Elliott McClure; National Science Foundation; New Guinea; New York Zoological Society; Northeastern Bird Banding Association; Bodil Schmidt-Nielsen; Per Scholander; Scripps Institution of Oceanography; Otto Soemarwoto; Charles Sibley; Rod Suthers; University of California, San Diego; Universitat Munchen; Gregorio T. Velasquez; Hobart van Deusen; Peter and Helen Waser; Zweifel
  - Arctic Aeromedical Laboratory (Box 14, Folder 142)
    Cornell University; Fairbanks, Alaska; insulation physiology; Ladd Air Force Base; Leeds and Northrup Co.; Office of Naval Research; Alan Burton; Harold Theodore Hammel; J. H. Heim; Major Andres Karstens; Harry Johnson; Kenneth Rawson; Kaare Rodahl; Peter Morrison, University of Wisconsin; University of Western Ontario Faculty of Medicine; Wood
  - Arctic Research Laboratory (Box 14, Folder 143)
    Point Barrow, Alaska; bird orientation; Office of Naval Research; Per Scholander; Woods Hole Oceanography Institute; Kenneth Rawson; Col. Walter Wood; Harold Theodore Hammel; Cornell University; Raymond J. Hock; Martin Karplus; British Joint Services Mission
  - Austin Ornithological Research Station (Box 15, Folder 144)
    Oliver L. Austin, Sr.; Maurice Brown; Fred Packard; Cape Cod, MA; Penikese Island; Maine; New Brunswick; bird banding; Massachusetts Division of Fisheries and Game; U.S. Biological Survey; Seth Low; U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service
  - Bat Banding (Box 15, Folder 145)
    Audubon Nature Center; Bird-Lore; Boy Scouts of America; Carnegie Institute; Chester Emory Mines; Dartmouth College; Dick Dow; John S. Hall; Harold B. Hitchcock; Richard Kolseth; Robert S. Luce; Mashpee Indian; Massachusetts Department of Conservation; Middlebury College; Mohonk Mountain House; National Band and Tag Co.; National Museum of Natural History; New York State College for Teachers; New York State Museum; Philadelphia Zoological Gardens; Phillips Academy Nature Club; pigeons; Royal Ontario Museum of Zoology; Werner Ruppell; Salt Lake Stamp Co.; Harold Trapido; U. S. Department of Interior; University of Massachusetts; University of New Hampshire; University of Western Ontario; Richard L. Weaver; Woods Hole; Worcester Natural History Society; Zoologisches Museum, Berlin
  - Beebe Tropical Research Station (Box 15, Folder 146)
    Simla, Trinidad; bats; butterflies; crabs; Michael Beecher; Jack Bradbury; Marc Buchanan; Kay Campbell; Julia Chase; Jocelyn Crane; Dorothy Dunning; Paul Ehrlich; Michael Emsley; Sir Lindsay Grant; John Hall; Jeremy Hatch; Nina Leen; Inger; H. Markl; Rich Penney; William Stiles; Nobuo Suga; Rod Suthers; Timothy and Janet Williams; William Wimsatt; National Science Foundation; New York Zoological Society; Rockefeller University; Time-Life
  - Bowdoin Scientific Station (Box 15, Folder 147)
    bird homing; Kent Island; Bay of Fundy, New Brunswick, Canada; J. W. Blunt; Edgar Folk; Dr. Gross; Rex Harris; Charles Huntington; Ernest Joy; Henry Kittredge; New Brunswick Museum